# Aleksandr Drozd

curriculum vitae

Tokyo, Japan Shinagawa ku ⑤ mobile +81-80-4332-5304 ⋈ alex@blackbird.pw ช blackbird.pw



#### **Brief Profile**

My research interests lie at the intersections of **artificial intelligence**, especially areas like natural language processing and artificial life, and **high performance computing**. In addition to academic background I have strong software development skills and experience.

## Education

2010-2014 Ph.D., Tokyo Institute of Technology, Graduate School of Information Science and

Technology, Tokyo.

Thesis title: "Memory-Conscious Optimizations for Sorting and Sequence Alignment for Massively

Parallel Heterogeneous Architectures."

2000-2005 Specialist degree (M.Sc. equivalent), Moscow State University.

Thesis title: "Semantic Pseudo-Code: Approach to Meaning-Base Search."

## Work Experience

2018.05-onwards Invited Researcher at AIST-Tokyo Tech Real World Big-Data Computation Open

Innovation Laboratory (RWBC-OIL)

2018.04-onwards Researcher at Tokyo Institute of Technology, School of Computing, Department of

Mathematical and Computing Science

Responsibilities: scientific research in areas of artificial intelligence and high performance computing.

2014.04-2018.03 Researcher at Tokyo Institute of Technology, Global Scientific Information and Com-

puting Center.

Responsibilities: developing algorithms for extreme-scale data-intensive computing.

2005.06-2010.05 Lecturer / Senior Lecturer (from 2008) at Moscow State University (Sevastopol

Branch, http://www.msusevastopol.net/), Programming Department.

Responsibilities: teaching courses on Parallel Data Processing, Operating Systems and Computer

Graphics.

2006.09-2009.06 Software Architect and Developer at Outsourcing Ukraine

(http://www.outsourcing-ukraine.com/), Sevastopol

Responsibilities: design and implementation of commercial software (C + +/C#)

## Fellowships and Grants

- o JSPS KAKENHI Grant number JP17K12739 adopted FY 2017: "Corpora on Demand: Scalable Methods of Obtaining Linguistic Data".
- Japanese Government (Monbukagakusho) scholarship for conducting PhD research 2010-2014.

### Research Interests

My current focus is on the intersection of the high performance computing (HPC) and intelligent data processing in various applied tasks. The areas in which I have worked (both by myself and in collaboration with experts in these areas) include:

- Natural language processing and computational linguistics: work in the context of vector space models
  framework from engineering high-performance construction of word embedding to applying various
  deep learning method for text understanding.
- o Other aspects of artificial intelligence: large scale deep learning for video recognition, artificial life modeling, swarming behaviour, social simulations.
  - In the past I have also been working in such areas as
- o Core HPC methods: algorithmic kernels for large scale data processing, e.g. distributed sorting
- o Computational biology: high-performance processing of big genomic data on accelerators

# Software Development and Other Relevant Skills

I am a passionate programmer who does a fair amount of coding for research and sometimes for fun.

- Coding/Software Development: My experience as a developer of commercial software gave me such skills as object oriented design, patterns and development processes.
- C, C++ (including C++14 standard), along with such libraries and tools for parallel programming as CUDA, OpenMP, MPI, OpenCL, TBB, etc for performance-critical parts.
- o **Python** for everything else: high level scripting, quick prototyping and such. Being open-source enthusiast I'm trying to contribute back to the Python ecosystem.
- I have experience with databases (SQL and noSQL), web technologies and version control systems, computer algebra and publishing systems.
- o I use machine learning extensively from basic statistical analysis methods to artificial neural networks.

# Other Related Activities

Organized workshops and tutorials:

- "Deep Learning from HPC Perspectives: Opportunities and Challenges" Mini-Symposium at SIAM PP 2018 conference.
- o "Distributional Compositional Semantics in the Age of Word Embeddings: Tasks, Resources and Methodology". Tutorial 4 at LREC 2018 conference.

Other activities:

- I have served as a program committee member of a number of conferences and workshops, including NAACL, \*SEM, SC, ISC, PARCO among others.
- From 2017 I serve as one of the organizers of "Tokyo Machine Learning Gym" meetup.

	Languages		Interests
Russian	native	Music	I play cello, guitar, and sing
English	fluent	${\sf Photography}$	Taking pictures of people and events
Japanese	conversational		nttp://nightwind.in
Ukrainian	conversational	Sport	Hiking, mountaineering, martial arts

### Selected Publications

- Marzena Karpinska, Bofang Li, Anna Rogers and Aleksandr Drozd. Subcharacter Information in Japanese Embeddings: When Is It Worth It?. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Relevance of Linguistic Structure in Neural Architectures for NLP (RELNLP) 2018 at ACL 2018. Melbourne, Australia. To appear.
- Bofang Li and Aleksandr Drozd. Subword-Level Composition Functions for Learning Word Embeddings.
   *Proceedings of The 2nd Workshop on Subword and Character level models in NLP (SCLeM)* at NAACL 2018. To appear.
- Bofang Li, Tao Liu, Zhe Zhao, Buzhou Tang, Aleksandr Drozd, Anna Rogers and Xiaoyong Du. Investigating Different Syntactic Context Types and Context Representations for Learning Word Embeddings. Proceedings of the 2017 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP). pp 2421–2431.
- Anna Rogers, Aleksandr Drozd and Bofang Li. The (too Many) Problems of Analogical Reasoning with Word Vectors. In Proceedings of the 6th Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics (\*SEM 2017), Association for Computational Linguistics, pp 135–148, Vancouver, Canada.
- o Aleksandr Drozd, Anna Gladkova, Satoshi Matsuoka. Word Embeddings, Analogies, and Machine Learning: Beyond King Man + Woman = Queen. Proceedings of COLING 2016, the 26th International Conference on Computational Linguistics: Technical Papers, pp 3519–3530, Osaka, Japan, December 11-17 2016
- o Mateusz Bysiek, Aleksandr Drozd and Satoshi Matsuoka. Migrating Legacy Fortran to Python While Retaining Fortran-Level Performance through Transpilation and Type Hints. Proceedings of PyHPC 16: the 6th Workshop on Python for High-Performance and Scientific Computing. pp 9-18.
- Aleksandr Drozd, Anna Gladkova, Satoshi Matsuoka. Discovering Aspectual Classes of Russian Verbs in Untagged Large Corpora. The 2015 IEEE International Conference on Data Science and Data Intensive Systems (DSDIS 2015), At Sydney, Australia, Dec 2015, pp 61 - 68.
- o Aleksandr Drozd, Anna Gladkova, Satoshi Matsuoka. Python, Performance and Natural Language Processing. 5th Workshop on Python for High-Performance and Scientific Computing, at Austin, Texas, USA, Nov 2015 in conjunction with SC15, pp 1-10.
- Aleksandr Drozd, Olaf Witkowski, Satoshi Matsuoka, Takashi Ikegami. Signal-Driven Swarming: A
  Parallel Implementation of Evolved Autonomous Agents to Perform A Foraging Task Proceedings of
  SWARM 2015 The First International Symposium on Swarm Behavior and Bio-Inspired Robotics,
  Kyoto, Oct 2015.
- o Aleksandr Drozd, Satoshi Matsuoka. HPC and Interactive Big Data Analytics: Case Study of Distributional Semantics. *Proceedings of IPSJ SIG Technical Reports 2014-HPC-146, Naha, Oct 2014.*
- Hideyuki Shamoto, Koichi Shirahata, Aleksandr Drozd, Hitoshi Sato, Satoshi Matsuoka. Large-scale Distributed Sorting for GPU-based Heterogeneous Supercomputers. *Proceedings of 2014 IEEE Conference of Big Data, October 2014, pp 510 - 518.*
- Aleksandr Drozd, Miquel Pericàs, Satoshi Matsuoka. Efficient String Sorting on Multi- and Many-Core Architectures in Proceedings of IEEE 3rd International Congress on Big Data (2014), Anchorage, AK, pp 637 - 644.
- Aleksandr Drozd, Naoya Maruyama, Satoshi Matsuoka. Sequence Alignment on Massively Parallel Heterogeneous Systems in Proceedings of IEEE 26th International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium Workshops & PhD Forum (2012), pp. 2498 - 2501, ISBN 978-1-4673-0974-5

- Aleksandr Drozd, Naoya Maruyama, Satoshi Matsuoka. A Multi GPU Read Alignment Algorithm with Model-Based Performance Optimization, Springer's Lecture Notes in Computer Science N7851 (2012), pages 270-277.
- o Aleksandr Drozd, Naoya Maruyama, Satoshi Matsuoka. Fast GPU Read Alignment with Burrows Wheeler Transform Based Index, *In Companion Proceeding of SC'11 Conference on High Performance Computing Networking, Storage and Analysis, 2011, Pages 21-22*.
- Aleksandr Drozd, Naoya Maruyama, Satoshi Matsuoka. Fast Read Alignment with Burrows Wheeler Transform: the GPU Perspective, In Proceedings of the 24th Summer United Workshops on Parallel, Distributed, and Cooperative Processing (SWoPP 2011), August 2011.
- o Anna Gladkova and Aleksandr Drozd. Towards Easier Querying of XML-based Linguistic Corpora, Taurida Bulletin of Mathematics and Informatics. #2, 2009, pages 71-77